## RICARDO ALBERTO PÉREZ CANDELAS

# SITE RELIABILITY ENGINEER & SENIOR DEVOPS PRACTITIONER

me@ricardoperezcandelas.com 5568583198 https://medium.com/@elrichartl

Site Reliability Engineer, Full-stack software developer with 5+ years industry experience specializing in back-end development and devops. Born and raised in Texcoco, Mexico State, I enjoy playing and following college football and flag football, amateur guitar and drums player, mindfull and successfull books, motorcycles and mechanics, I love cafe racer, brat and bobber style.

## </> > SKILLS

WEB JAVASCRIPT HTML 5 CSS MVC REST

JAVASCRIPT NODE.JS JQUERY BOOTSTRAP REACT.JS BACKBONE.JS REACT NATIVE

DATABASE MYSQL POSTGRESQL NOSQL ORM

DEVOPS

AWS DIGITALOCEAN DOCKER COMPOSE CI/CD JENKINS GITLAB BITBUCKET GCP

KUBERNETES MAKISU PROJECT HELM HARNESS JENKINS PIPELINES TERRAFORM

BACKEND REST JSON API DESIGN PATTERNS TDD

PROJECT AGILE GITHUB TEAMWORK LEADER GITFLOW GITHUB FLOW

## EMPLOYMENT

#### Senior DevOps Engineer,

Globant

Making and follow DevOps practices and culture

- Leadership
- DevOps practitioner

Docker Kubernetes DevOps Terraform AWS Jenkins Gitlab Ruby Bash Groovy Prometheus

#### Azure DevOps Senior, Readymind

Making and follow DevOps practices and culture

• Team leader

Docker Kubernetes DevOps Terraform Azure Azure Pipelines Gitlab Bash Groovy

#### Site Reliability Engineer II,

#### Wizeline

Making and follow DevOps practices and culture

- Work with internationa team remotly
- First one DevOpsDays in Mexico 2020 core-organizer
- Contribute to internal projects
- Estudy GCP and AWS proffessional certifications

2022-01 — Present

2021-07 — 2022-01

2019-09 — 2021-07

Docker Kubernetes DevOps Terraform AWS GCP Organizer SCRUM Jenkins Harness Gitlab Ruby Bash Groovy

#### Team Leader, Nimanic

2018-03 — 2019-09

Software Team Leader Engineer and Cloud Operator

- Learn internet of things protocols and communication
- Start with Agile practices
- Learn startup cycle and releases
- Start implementation of continuous delivery and deployment
- Migration of all production environment from Heroku to AWS
- Implement high availability

Ruby MQTT Lead Heroku AWS Telematics Jenkins SCRUM React Native PHP AWS Node, is React. JS Redux Workflow CI/CD

#### Team Leader, Mellow Consulting

2017-09 — 2018-03

Tech Team leader at Mellow Consulting, leading an 8 people team

- Lead a tech team of 8 people
- Implement workflows and process for development
- Talk with clients to create products
- Plan, propose and implement digital solutions for client requirements with designers and marketing teams
- Teach and propose solutions to developer team
- Apply agile techniques for meets and project teams

Agile Lead SCRUM React Native PHP AWS Node, js React. JS Redux Workflow CI/CD

## Ruby on Rails Developer, Tech Leader, Vinco

2016-11 — 2017-09

#### Orbis

Ruby developer with Ruby on Rails Framework for education projects

- Lead a team of 2 people
- Teach to junior developers best practices
- Use TDD and CI/CD
- Use docker for create development environments

Lead Ruby on Rails Ruby CircleCi CI/CD TDD Rspec SCRUM

## PHP Developer, Vinco

2015-04 — 2016-11

#### Orbis

PHP developer on Wordpress, Prestashop and vanilla PHP projects

- Create templates
- Paticipate in a team for international client

PHP Wordpress Prestashop

## Software Developer, Coordinación General de Formación e Innovación Educativa (CGFIE), Instituto Politécnico Nacional (IPN)

2015-01 — 2015-12

I participated on numerous Vanilla PHP projects to teach to IPN community, I used git, gitlab, docker

- I worked on a local PHP MVC framework for standarized team workflow
- I installed a basic CentOS server for local use
- I proposed use the github workflow for developer team and created many manual for best development and deploy practices

PHP Linux MVC Codeigniter Git Gitlab Docker

#### México

Trainee developer, I participated on Ruby on Rails projects with PostgreSQL and Agile development techniques

- Participated on project for a big ensurance company
- I understood the MVC and Design Patterns

Agile Ruby Ruby on Rails PostgreSQL SCRUM HTML CSS MySQL PHP



## **★** PROJECTS

#### Site Reliability Engineer, Itau Cuenta Digital

2022-01 — Present

In this project I had many chances to try and implement some technologies and solutions with previous research and presentation to my client's DevOps teams

Jenkins AWS Docker Kubernetes Terraform Prometheus CI CD Gitlab Api Connect Ownership

#### Site Reliability Engineer, DevOps Practitioner, AbInbev DevOps

2021-07 — 2022-01

#### Latam

My stance here was short although I learn too much about team management and deal with a Global team to adopt technical methologies, I learn more about soft skils such as speaking to many teams an deal deadlines though

Azure DevOps Backstage Leadership Ownership Self-management Team management

#### Site Reliability Engineer, Exemplar,

2019-11 — 2021-07

#### Metis

We need to analyze, plan and implement DevOps best practices such CI/CD, make pipelines and use Continuous deployment tools

Jenkins OKTA AWS GCP Docker Kubernetes Terraform Harness New Relic CI CD

#### Tech Leader and Backend Developer, Creator API

2017-04 — 2017-08

Product for build interactive lessons for kids with multimedia resources from Youtube, Khan Academy Lite, Wikipedia, Red Magsiterial, Google Images

Education Ruby Docker Python Microservices Test Unit Rspec Continuous Integration Continuous Delivery API

## Devops and backend developer, khan-lite-

2017-06

#### backend

Microservice for serve resources from Khan Academy Lite installation, build with ruby and docker containers Education Ruby Docker Microservices Ruby on Rails API

#### Devops and backend developer, wikidownload

2017-06

Microservice for serve pdf from Wikipedia article, build with python and docker containers Education Docker Microservices Django Django Rest Framework API

## Back-end developer, Grubertek API

2016-09 — 2017-04

**RESTFUL API for Grubertek** 

PHP PHPUnit Vagrant Test Unit Continuous Integration Continuous Delivery API

## Developer, SudoVerbs

2017-05

Bash console utility for learn english verbs

**Bash Shell Education** 

## Developer, tech lead, team lead, Royal Licoreria a

#### Domicilio

Platform for deliver alcohol with hibrid and native mobile apps

React Native Redux Node MySQL Loopback App IOs Android

## Developer, tech lead, team lead, Simulador Reto

## **ENARM**

Simulator for ENARM test, this simulator helps to medics to study for ENARM test

React Redux Node MySQL Loopback Node Docker Docker Compose

#### Developer, tech lead, team lead,

#### **Autounion**

This platform helps to agencies and customers to sell and find options for buy a car

React Redux Node PostgreSQL Loopback Node Docker Docker Compose Django

## 2017-09 — Present

2017-09 — Present

2017-09 — Present

## **EDUCATION**

#### BSCS, Universidad Autónoma del Estado de México

Branch on Software Development

#### 2010-06 — 2014-12

## EXTRACURRICULAR

#### Organizer / Speaker, Docker Meetup **CDMX**

- Monthly speaker on docker meet
- Free Docker Courses organizer and speaker

#### Core Organizer, DevOpsDays Guadalajara Mexico 2020

- The First one event like this in Mexico
- Get sponsorships
- Made community events to get more exposure

Guadalajara, México 2020-03 — Present

CDMX, México 2017-03 — Present

## Enchiladas DevOps Podcast, Co-

#### Host

- Make scripts for interviews
- Get guests to interview
- Make logo
- Edit and upload all episodes
- Get sponsorships
- Expose community events in social media
- Make community posts

CDMX, México 2019-12 — Present

Si no son enchiladas podcast, Host

CDMX, México 2020-03 — Present

- Make scripts for interviews
- Make logo
- Edit and upload all episodes

## WRITING

## El porque las pruebas unitarias no sirven, Medium 2017 La diferencia entre rake y rails, 2017 Medium Un paso obligado para ser un desarrollador 'Pro', 2017 Medium **SPEAKING** ReactJS Basic 2017 Course, • I teached to 10 people the first steps to ReactJS Docker Basic Course, Docker Meetup Course 2017 CDMX

• I spoke front of 100 people teaching the first steps to Docker technology